Dorothy Sears Ainsworth Papers, 1894-1976
Smith College Archives
- Series IV. Organizations
  - International Association of Physical Education and Sports for Girls and Women (IAPESGW) (Box 19)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-Plewes, Doris 1958-62 (Box 23)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-Pribitzer, Helena 1954-58 (Box 23)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-R 1948-61 (Box 23)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-Romero-Brest 1951-62 (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-S 1947-60 (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-Schneider, Elsa 1952-60 (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-Sepa, Milica 1954-61 (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-Shirley, Mabel 1957-61 (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-Singer, Gusta 1951-63 (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-T 1948-64 (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-Todd, Frances 1953-54 (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-Todd, Frances 1955-58 (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-U 1948-69 (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-V 1948-69 (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-W 1948-61 (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-Webster, Muriel 1952-61 (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence-Miscellaneous 1948-49 (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Correspondence to Representatives 1950-62 (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Executive Committee (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-Form Letters, Miscellaneous (Box 24)
    - IAPESGW-History (Box 25)
    - IAPESGW-Journees D'Etude de Boulouris 1958 (Box 25)
    - IAPESGW-Membership (Box 25)
    - IAPESGW-Newsletters 1950-55 (Box 25)
    - IAPESGW-Newsletters 1956-64 (Box 25)
    - IAPESGW-Officers (Box 25)
    - IAPESGW-Photographs-A-I (Box 25)
    - IAPESGW-Photographs-N-T (Box 25)
    - IAPESGW-The Review (Box 25)
    - IAPESGW-Teacher Exchange 1940s-50s (Box 25)
    - IAPESGW and UNESCO (Box 25)
  - International Council on Health, Physical Education and Recreation (ICHPER) (Box 25)
    - ICHPER-Agenda (Box 25)
    - ICHPER-Asian Journal (Box 25)
    - ICHPER-Bulletin (incomplete) 1961-70 (Box 25)
    - ICHPER-Constitution, Amendments, Resolutions (Box 25)
    - ICHPER-Congress-Amsterdam (1 of 2) 1960 (Box 26)
    - ICHPER-Congress-Amsterdam (2 of 2) 1960 (Box 26)
    - ICHPER-Congress-New Delhi 1961 (Box 26)
    - ICHPER-Congress-Addis Ababa 1965, (2 photographs) (Box 26)
    - ICHPER-Congress-Dublin 1968 (Box 26)
    - ICHPER-Congress-Abidjan 1969 (Box 26)
    - ICHPER-Congress-Sydney 1970 (Box 26)
    - ICHPER-Congress-Kingston 1971 (Box 26)
    - ICHPER-Congress-London 1972 (Box 26)
    - ICHPER-Congress-Bali 1973 (Box 26)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-A, B 1960-69 (Box 26)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-C, D 1960-73 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-Ciszek, Raymond 1964-72 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-E, F 1959-68 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-Francois, Pierre 1955-64 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-G-I 1961-71 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-J, K 1960-67 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-Joseph, P.M. 1959-64 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-L, N 1958-72 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-Melanfy, Michael 1958-61 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-P-S 1960-71 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-T-Z 1960-73 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-Thomas, Sylvester J. 1958-62 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-Thorensen, Klas 1959-64 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-Troester, Carl (1 of 2) 1958-68 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-Troester, Carl (2 of 2) 1969-73 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Correspondence-Webster, Muriel 1962-65 (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-History (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Letters of Appreciation 1960s (Box 27)
    - ICHPER-Lists of Organizations and People (Box 28)
    - ICHPER-Organization and Miscellaneous (Box 28)
    - ICHPER-Periodic Physical Education Questionnaire (Box 28)
    - ICHPER-Printed Letters 1960s (Box 28)
    - ICHPER-Reports (Box 28)
    - ICHPER-Reports-Leisure Time Activities of Youth in the Americas 1964 (Box 28)
    - ICHPER-Resume, Vita (Box 28)
  - International Council of Sports and Physical Education 1950s (Box 28)
  - International Council of Sports and Physical Education 1960s (Box 28)
  - Japan International Christian University Foundation (Box 28)
  - Massachusetts Association for Health, Physical Education, and Recreation-Journal Fall 1969 (Box 28)
  - National Amateur Athletic Association Women's Division (Box 28)
  - National Association of Physical Education and Recreation-India (Box 28)
  - National Association for Physical Education for College Women (NAPECW) (Box 28)
    - NAPECW-Board of Directors (Box 28)
    - NAPECW-Correspondence (Box 28)
    - NAPECW-International Affairs Report 1947 (Box 28)
    - NAPECW-International Meetings (Box 28)
    - NAPECW-Report 1947 (Box 29)
  - National Council of Women-Correspondence (Box 29)
  - National Council of Women-Photographs (Box 29)
  - National Council of Women-Minutes, Meetings, Agenda 1956-60 (Box 29)
  - National Council of Women-Miscellaneous (Box 29)
  - National Education Association 1950s (Box 29)
  - National Education Association of U.S. and American Association of School Administration-Policies (Box 29)
  - National Foundation for Health, Physical Education and Recreation (Box 29)
  - Ohio Association of Health, Physical Education and Recreation 1954 (Box 29)
  - Oregon Association of Health, Physical Education and Recreation-Creed (Box 29)
  - Pan American Association of Professors of Physical Education 1950s (Box 29)
  - Pan American Congress of Physical Education 1940s-50s (Box 29)
  - Pan American Union (Box 30)
  - Philippine Association of Physical Education and Sports for Girls and Women 1971 (Box 30)
  - Scottish Council of Physical Education (Box 30)
  - Shree Hanuman Vyayam Prasarak Mandal 1950s-60s (Box 30)
  - UNESCO (Box 30)
    - UNESCO-Correspondence (Box 30)
    - UNESCO-Helsinki Meeting, Abstract 1959 (Box 30)
    - UNESCO-Helsinki Meeting-Papers, Reports, Recommendations (Box 30)
    - UNESCO-Helsinki Meeting-Plans, Procedures, Programs 1950 (Box 30)
    - UNESCO-Miscellaneous (Box 30)
    - UNESCO-Printed Materials (Box 30)
    - UNESCO-Questionnaire (Box 30)
    - UNESCO-World Organization of Physical Education Organizations (Box 30)
    - UNESCO-Youth Institute 1957 (Box 30)
  - UNICEF (Box 30)
  - U.S. Field Hockey Association-South Africa 1950s (Box 30)
  - World Confederation of Organizations of Teaching Profession (WCOTP) (Box 30)
    - WCOTP-Annual Meeting 1958-65 (Box 30)
    - WCOTP-Correspondence 1951-60 (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Correspondence-Carr, William G. 1958-64 (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Correspondence-Troester, Carl A. 1958-63 (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Correspondence-Welty, Paul S. 1959-60 (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Echo 1958-63 (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Meeting-Rome 1958 (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Meeting-Washington 1959 (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Meeting-Amsterdam 1960 (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Meeting-New Delhi 1961 (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Meeting-Liberia 1962 (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Meeting-Stockholm 1962 (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Meeting-Korea 1966 (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Meeting-Delegate Assembly 1969 (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-General (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Reports, Miscellaneous (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Resolutions (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Working Papers-Stockholm 1962 (Box 31)
    - WCOTP-Working Papers-Seoul 1966 (Box 32)
- Series V. Conferences
  - International Union for Health Education of the Public 1950s-60s (Box 32)
  - International Congress of Sport Science 1964 (Box 32)
  - International Congress-Physical Education, Recreation, Rehabilitation 1948 (Box 32)
  - 11th International Congress on Women's Physical Education and Sports (in German and French only) (Box 32)
  - International League for Modern Gymnastics 1950s (Box 32)
  - International Relations in Health, Physical Education and Recreation 1950 (Box 32)
  - Linigad-Program 1949 (Box 32)
  - Linigad-Correspondence 1956 (Box 32)
  - Linigad-Correspondence, Review 1952 (Box 32)
  - National Conference on Graduate Study in Health Education, Physical Education and Recreation 1950? (Box 32)
  - Conference: Report of the committee to Survey Doctoral Programs in Physical Education (National Conference on Graduate Study in Health Education, Physical Education and Recreation?) (Box 32)
  - Washington 1947 (Box 32)
- Series VI. Writings
  - Notes (Box 32)
  - Printed Material (Box 32)
  - Publications (Box 33)
  - Typescripts 1949-69, undated (Box 33)
  - Bibliography (Box 33)
  - Speeches (Box 33)
  - Speeches 1928-63 (Box 33)
  - Speeches 1964-69, undated (Box 33)
  - History of Physical Education-Transcripts (Box 33)
  - History of Physical Education-Notebook (Box 34)
  - Miscellaneous undated (Box 34)
  - Miscellaneous 1951-67 (Box 34)
- Series VII. Subject Files, A-Z
  - Accreditation (Box 34)
  - Address Lists (Box 34)
  - Amherst College-PE (Box 34)
  - Anatomy-The Human Factory by Fritz Kahn (Box 34)
  - Aquatics and Analysis of Camp Timber Ridge 1954, undated (Box 34)
  - Archery-Student Paper 1947 (Box 34)
  - Bibliography (Box 34)
  - Brazilian Dance Group 1950-51 (Box 34)
  - Building Plan (Box 34)
  - Camping (Box 35)
  - Curriculum (Box 35)
  - Competition (Box 35)
  - Coeducation in Physical Education-Student Papers (Box 35)
  - Dance-Student Papers (Box 35)
  - Dance-Photographs (Box 35)
  - Dance "Rhythmic Form and Analysis" by M. H'Doubler 1932 (Box 35)
  - Democracy (Box 35)
  - Discipline (Box 35)
  - Disturbed Children and Physical Education-Report of an Experimental Study by Sheila Cater 1954-55 (Box 35)
  - Driver Education (Box 35)
  - Drug Abuse (Box 35)
  - Education-International (Box 36)
  - Education and Physical Education (Box 36)
  - Elementary School Physical Education (Box 36)
  - Exercises (Box 36)
  - Federal Relations to Education (Box 36)
  - Films (Box 36)
  - Fitness (Box 36)
  - Golf-Student Paper (Box 36)
  - Graduate Education (Box 36)
  - Greater Boston Community Council (Box 36)
  - Gymnastics (Box 36)
  - Health Education (Box 36)
  - Havalanta Games, Atlanta 1952 (Box 36)
  - Human Rights (Box 36)
  - International Education (Box 36)
  - Kinsey Reports-Educational Implications (Box 37)
  - Lewis, Dio-Student Paper (Box 37)
  - Military Training-Women (Box 37)
  - Movement (Box 37)
  - New Mexico Physical Education (Box 37)
  - Newsletter-Educator's Dispatch, Washington, D.C. 1949-51 (Box 37)
  - Outing Clubs (Box 37)
  - People to People (Box 37)
  - Physical Education-History and Theory-Student Papers (1 of 3) (Box 37)
  - Physical Education-History and Theory-Student Papers (2 of 3) (Box 37)
  - Physical Education-History and Theory (3 of 3) (Box 37)
  - Physical Education-Student Papers, Miscellaneous Reports (1 of 2) (Box 38)
  - Physical Education-Student Papers, Miscellaneous Reports (2 of 2) (Box 38)
  - Playgrounds (Box 38)
  - President's Council on Physical Fitness (Box 38)
  - Recreation (Box 38)
  - Riding (Box 38)
  - S-Miscellaneous Topics (Box 38)
  - Sargent College-Student Paper (Box 38)
  - Sex Education (Box 38)
  - Skiing-Student Paper (Box 38)
  - Sports in Women's Colleges-by Janet Owen-Student Paper and Published Article (Box 38)
  - Study on Academic Credit (Box 38)
  - Wetzel Grid (Box 38)
  - Wood, Thomas Dennison-Student Paper (Box 38)
  - International Countries (Box 39)
    - Argentina (Box 39)
    - Australia (Box 39)
    - Austria (Box 39)
    - Belgium (Box 39)
    - Brazil-Photographs (Box 39)
    - Burma (Box 39)
    - Canada (Box 39)
    - Chile (Box 39)
    - China (1 of 2) (Box 39)
    - China (2 of 2) (Box 39)
    - Costa Rica-"Workshop in Comparative Physical Education" by Ainsworth (Box 39)
    - Cuba (Box 40)
    - Czechoslovakia (Box 40)
    - Denmark-Photograph (Box 40)
    - England (Box 40)
    - Estonia (Box 40)
    - Fiji Islands (Box 40)
    - Finland (Box 40)
    - France (1 of 2) (Box 40)
    - France (2 of 2) (Box 40)
    - Germany (1 of 2) (Box 40)
    - Germany (2 of 2) (Box 41)
    - Greece (Box 41)
    - Guatemala (Box 41)
    - India (Box 41)
    - Ireland (Box 41)
    - Israel (Box 41)
    - Italy (Box 41)
    - Japan (Box 41)
    - Liberia (Box 41)
    - Netherlands (Box 41)
    - Norway (Box 41)
    - Peru-"The Necessity to Play with both Hands" by Felix Mateo (Box 41)
    - Philippines (1 of 2) (Box 41)
    - Philippines-Physical Education Today, Manila (2 of 2) 1958-59 (Box 42)
    - Poland (Box 42)
    - Puerto Rico (Box 42)
    - South Africa (Box 42)
    - Sweden (Box 42)
    - Switzerland (Box 42)
    - USSR (Box 42)
    - Uruguay (Box 42)
- Series VIII. Awards, Photographs, and Scrapbooks
  - General, Press Releases (Box 42)
  - List of Awards Received (Box 42)
  - American Council of Administrators, Health, Physical Education, and Recreation (Box 42)
  - Distinguished Service Award 1925 (Box 42)
  - Gymnastic Peoples College (#C) 1927 (Box 42)
  - AAHPER, Life Member (#D) 1944 (Box 42)
  - AAHPER, Honor Fellow (#E) 1949 (Box 42)
  - Letters from A.A. Presidents 1959-60 (Box 42)
  - Letters of Recognition Presented by the Department of Physical Education 1960 (Box 42)
  - Cross of Honor, Finland (#13) 1961 (Box 42)
  - Massachusetts Association of AAHPER-State Award (#F) 1961 (Box 42)
  - Central High School Girls' Recreation Association-Honorary Lifetime Member 1962 (#G) (Box 42)
  - Hetherington Award (American Academy of Physical Education) (#16) 1962 (Box 42)
  - Eastern District Association District Honor Award (#H) 1964 (Box 42)
  - Inspiring Leadership (#19) 1965 (Box 42)
  - NFHPER-Charter Member 1966 (Box 42)
  - Woman of Conscience Award (#22) 1968 (Box 42)
  - NAPECW-Honorary Life Membership (#J) 1970 (Box 42)
  - Patent of Decoration, Japan 1970 (Box 42)
  - AAHPER 1974 (Box 42)
  - Presidential Service Award (#27) 1974 (Box 42)
  - Recognition Award-People-to-People 1974 (Box 42)
  - Smith College-Doctor of Science (#9) (Box 42)
  - Photographs (Box 42)
    - Photographs 1910s-20s (Box 42)
    - Photographs 1930s (Box 42)
    - Photographs 1940s (Box 42)
    - Photographs 1950s (Box 42)
    - Photographs 1960s (Box 42)
    - Photographs 1970s (Box 42)
    - Photographs: Ainsworth (Box 42)
    - Photographs: Retirement Party 1960 (Box 42)
    - Photographs: IAPESGW, AAHPER, Japan (Box 42)
    - Photographs: Brazil, University of-Dance Group 1951 (Box 42)
    - Photographs: Possibly related to Iran Plaque (#K) 1971? (Box 42)
    - Photographs: Japan Album (Box 43)
    - Photographs: Daily Calendar 1970 (Box 43)
    - Photographs: EAPECW? TOKYO (on foam board) 1970s (Box 43)
    - Photographs: IAPESGW (on foam board) 1970s (Box 43)
    - Photographs: Album 1950s-60s (Box 44)
  - Ainsworth Christmas Greeting detailing her trips 1966 (Box 44)
  - Scrapbook: IAPESGW-Sixth International Congress 1969 (Box 44)
  - Scrapbook: Europe, Grecourt 1910s, (photographs) (Box 44)
  - Scholarship Fund (#N) (Box 44)
  - Fourth Class of the Order of the Precious Crown, Japan (#26) 1970 (Box 44)
  - Versailles Medal #(8) 1953 (Box 44)
  - Certificate from the Class of 1916 at 60th Reunion (#M) 1976 (Box 44)
  - Award: Columbia University-Master of Arts (#A) 1925 (Box 44)
  - Award: Columbia University-Academic Degree-Teacher of Physical Education (#B) 1925 (Box 44)
  - Award: Certificate (Medal of Honor) from Minister of Education, France (#16a) 1953 (Box 44)
  - Award: Smith College (M?) (Box 44)
  - Gulick Medal of AAHPER (#10) 1960 (Box 45)
  - Gift from AAHPER (#23) 1969 (Box 45)
  - Medal from Versailles (#8) 1953 (Box 45)
  - Tokyo Metropolitan Government (#25) 1969 (Box 45)
  - President's Key AAHPER, "S" pin from Smith College Athletic Association (#1, 6, 12) 1950-61 (Box 45)
  - Silver Plate from Women Student's University of Copenhagen (#15) 1961 (Box 45)
  - Silver Bowl Awarded by CT Inter-School Athletic Committee Board of Control (#2) 1947-59 (Box 45)
  - Cross of Honor, Finland (#13) 1961 (Box 45)
  - R. Tait McKenzie Medal-AAHPER (#21) 1967 (Box 45)
  - R. Tait McKenzie Centennial (#20) 1967 (Box 45)
  - Merite Sportive-French Medal (#4) 1950 (Box 45)
  - Insignia of Commandeur of the Order "Du Merite Sportif" France (#14) 1961 (Box 45)
  - Detroit medal Celebrating Detroit's Foundation, Key to Detroit (#7) 1951 (Box 45)
  - Medal-Phling Svenska Gymnastikes Skapare, Sweden (Box 45)
  - Medal of Honor from Minister of Education, France (#16a) 1953 (Box 45)
  - Medal Fourth Class of the Order of the Precious Crown, Japan (#26) 1970 (Box 45)
  - Canadian Olympics 1976 (Box 45)
  - Ling Society-Lingiad Medal (#3) 1949 (Box 45)
  - Medal Given to Officers of AAHPER (#24) 1969 (Box 45)
  - Medal from Pan American Congress, Uruguay (#5) 1950 (Box 45)
  - Medal, Ribbon, and Pin from XVIII Olympics, Tokyo (#18) 1964 (Box 45)
  - 2 Medals Presented by Advanced Teacher Training School in France during the ICHPER Congress (#17) 1964 (Box 45)
  - 17 Printing plates from "The History of Physical Education in Colleges for Women" 1930 (Box 46)
  - 4 Printing plates-women in sports, and 40th Reunion woodcuts (Box 47)
  - Scrapbook: International Congress of Physical Education for Girls and Women, Paris 1953 (Box 48)
  - Scrapbook: International Congress of Physical Education 1954 (Box 48)
  - Scrapbook: International Congress of Physical Education for Girls and Women 1949 (Box 49)
  - Iran Commemoration Plaque (#K) 1971 (Box 49)
  - 2 paper and wood fans (Box 49)
  - Photographs: on foam board, and oversized (Box 50)
- Series IX. Audio-Visual
  - Hazel Peterson's interviews with Dorothy Ainsworth in preparation for dissertation and publication of Ainsworth's biography. (Box C710a)
    - Ainsworth's Early Life in Moline Illinois, Family Philosophy, Interests, May 29, 1964. B-With Smith Unit in France; Early Teaching and Prof. Training; Philosophy May 29, 1964. REQUEST AS: C710a (Box C710a)
    - Administrative Teaching, Sport Philosophy DSA May 31, 1964 Northampton. B-DSA qualities, Interests, Influences by sister Mrs. Getz, Moline June 10, 1964. REQUEST AS: C710b (Box C710b)
    - Influences, Interest, Activities, DSA March 1965 Dallas, Texas. B-Smith College Athletic Association DSA Accomplishments, Smith College; DSA March 1965 Dallas Texas Administrative Philosophy and Graduate Program Smith College. REQUEST AS: C710c (Box C710c)
    - Smith College teaching and Sports Programs, Facilities, Basketball; IAPESGW Early Organization. B-IAPESGW-WCOTP, ICHPER affairs-Return to Smith; Senda Berenson. REQUEST AS: C710d (Box C710d)
    - International Endeavors, Programs, Philosophy December, 1965 Northampton. B- International Activities 1947-53; Sport competition Philosophy, Smith Field Days, Rally Day December, 1965. REQUEST AS: C710e (Box C710e)
    - Smith College A.A. Activities, Awards, Admin. December 1965 Northampton. B-Additions, Corrections to Chapters March 1966 Chicago. REQUEST AS: C710f (Box C710f)
    - H. Aull and E. Jennings (33 min); Ruth Elliott (3min); Edith Hill (8 min. cont. side B) May, 1964. B-Edith Hill (16 min); Margaret Gicesson (Grierson?) (5 min); E.L. Bowles (6 min); Ann Delano (18 min) May 1964. REQUEST AS: C710g (Box C710g)
    - A- Ann Delano (5 min); M. Leland (24 min); Ruth Totman (6min); H. Hazelton (12 min) May 1964. B-Helen Hazelton (8 min); Ruth Evans (27 min) May 1964. REQUEST AS: C710h (Box C710h)